you also read many times it's a Chitina
meter is important it's important to see
your mind and stand in line so how what
is the best environment for that being
able to see your mind non-centrality
distraction not company so you can't see
your mind when you just constantly
income well most of your day is spent in
the company of others even if they are
all perfectly silent perfectly mindful
and retreat still it's others so if one
wants to see the sign of the mind one
needs to develop perceptions and solid
one needs to be secluded from sensuality
in terms of his not just his senses but
his mind as well cuz their debts that's
another thing like it's an exercise
somebody can do if they're not sure what
its member is but yeah imagine imagine
you you sort of you go to the unknown
area some forests from wild jungle and
you go there with ten people as a group
now imagine like what what is like the
basic the base is moved basis of your
mood how are you feeling at the time now
it's fine not necessarily I'm feeling
pleasant but just just overall what is
the sense what is the overall perception
as well of this group of us being in in
this environment now for the comparison
sake you go to the equally remote
unknown environment all alone and then
compare the difference in the basis of
that perception of that experience as a
whole and you'll see that there is
something fundamentally different when
you perceive yourself alone and when you
perceive yourself with at least one more
person or more more and it's that
difference that's the basis for the
right practice that's all each other now
once you discern that correctly then
sure even when you are with others you
would be alone but if you don't discern
that means even when you're alone you're
with others so in the basis of that
recognition of that existential solitude
obviously sense restraint and virtue
developed you start developing the you
start discerning that sense of the
general fundamentally enduring mood
you're in and that's what mind is
basically practically speaking closest
to what cheat days would be the most
general mood of your currently enduring
situation not like oh I feel something
my back or my knee hurts no overall mood
is it agreeable is it disagreeable is it
elated is it depressed is it sort of
coming is it sort of going is it
increasing is it faithful is it lust is
your anger is it night there is it
economy T and that's how the Buddha
described a mind as well
so it's it's it's it cannot be described
more accurately than in those general
terms which for some people might be a
bit ambiguous because they're not used
to discerning it like that hence they
know used to discerning what their mind
is so that's I mean you basically you
need certain basis of virtue solitude
and then that the signs of this enduring
mood regardless of what's particularly
happening are becoming more and more
visible the signs the signs of the mind
not the mind exactly exactly
you know oh that's my mind you see the
signs and tokens of the mind or a
contour which you get to discern the
mind
good one as I'm having lustful thoughts
I'm having angry complaining thoughts
lots of complaining and from that see
knowing that I am happy knowing that you
are actually thinking thoughts
complaining you know yeah so that's like
the first step you recognize okay my
mind is effectively complaining you
don't try to stop that we get rid of it
nor indulge it for that matter you're
not feeling it either you look what's
the basis of it so my mind is here it is
complaining so what's what underlines simultaneously
so what's what underlines simultaneously
this experience of of complaining mind
what underlies in its its discomfort
it's unpleasant if something is
unpleasant you feel displeasure in
regard to something
hence the symptom of complaining so in
that sense you're not concerned with
complaining is an issue you start
discerning as a sign and token eye as a
symptom of the underlying issue of the
mind trying to have avoid displeasure
same with anger same with anything
basically whether its sensuality again
oh mine wants this okay so those are you
can take that as an issue in itself as
an object in itself and they try to get
rid of it try to think the opposite do
is good luck with that
oh you could start what if I take this
as an indication of an underlying
problem which is the state of mind dead
I'm not aware of and thus reacting to it
giving in to the pressure of that mind
of that mood saying no
so if indicating it to mind is mops good
thing it isn't unless you develop it
it's certainly for somebody for / - Gina
the mind is always not pure because it's
always affected with wrong view so
that's what within their wrongness - to
Janine's to start discerning what is
less wrong and what what is less wrong
than greed aversion delusion is non
green on a version on delusion but yes
he's still affected with the wrong view
but because he found something less
wrong within that he can go even further
and make that less wrong when eventually
you abandon all the wrong crudely wrong
or things that are less wrong that's how
I develop the right view to
understanding the the fundamental nature
of the wrong view that's your right view
so you would discern you would discern
the starting point is is wrong but you
took instruction along a degree of faith
and so on and you stop practicing
reflection and then you studies learning
things that are less wrong but it's all
about I'm doing and in order to keep on
doing you need to keep seeing further
and further what what's what's this
underlying bye what's this something I'm
buying but the problem with petitioners
mind in general is he takes for granted
that what he thinks it's right it's
right while he the same time knows he's
not a sotapanna
but you have no such criteria which
means what you think it's right you
should not regard his rightness sadly
you should look what's underneath it as
the we would say delve with a knife keep
cutting in and cutting in and cutting in
not keep building more and more and more
until you get a perfect system that you
built in your mind so you you cannot
start rightly but it doesn't mean you
have to stay with the wrongness so to
speak you can't start rightly but you
can start less wrongly and less wrongly
and that's wrong and just back back to
the sound of the might sound of the mind
you say that that mind he's interested
well there was become apparent yeah yeah
if you start discerning that's the
problem whatever whatever served for Pluto
whatever whatever served for Pluto
Jinnah he jumps at it whatever he
perceives to his senses that's where
that that's what he attention goes
whatever mood arises that's what his
attention is but I'm saying is you you
want to stop being concerned with
particular problems you want to start
regarding them as indications of the
much broader much more fundamental
liability to the problem in the first
place in other words as I said for the
body in the example of why the
complaining mind
yeah you wanna stop complaining I'm not
watching my breath what matters then you
calm your mouth but that's just
management but instead of that when
complaining is present while complaining
is present through not engaging with
complaining but not trying to get rid of
it either you start to see it what is
this a symptom of so you stop regarding
symptoms as your illness you start
seeing them as indication of a much
broader less visible illness and that
illness is a mind effectively greed
minor factor without aversion
manufactory delusion once you start
seeing it on that level like indirectly
so to speak to begin with
you recognize oh it's because the mind
has a reason with this lust these are
the thoughts that are harassing me but
not because I want the thoughts I must
get rid of the thoughts that's how you
stop being affected by either you
realize and that satipatthana suit he
knows elated mind as you later my
depressed my as depressed mind yeah the
mind is depressed now not my problem
depressed mind has a corresponding
symptom of these type of thoughts not my
problem either that's how you overcome
your thinking not by trying to get rid
of it or controlling it but by seeing
what the basis of it is and abandoning
it you don't delight in what mind offers
you don't try to get rid of it you start
seeing it as an indications as symptoms
of the state of the mind it's currently
present because you would not even it's
unthinkable it's impossible the mind say
is in a non sensual mood yet your
perceptions of perceptions of sensuality
that's impossible
oh the mind is free from aversion and
yet you have thoughts of ill-will that's
impossible so thoughts available means
mind of aversion thoughts of sensuality
means thoughts of sensual pleasures in
mind of sensuality thoughts of
distraction carelessness whatever means
mind of basically indolence and delusion
so being aware of your thoughts
rightly having a right attitude not just
I'm aware what I'm thinking about
you have to start learning how to regard
them as an indication of the state of
mind not just oh this is this is
sensuality this is lust this is loss
it's all in permanent it's only
permanent I must look at the ugly to
look at the ugly no you must see the
basis of your sensual thoughts which is
the mind effective licensure it that's
high up through the central thoughts so
that's right the signs and tokens of the
mind and for that as we said virtue is
necessary you have to stop engaging at
face value with the prospect of what
your senses offer you prospect of
pleasure prospect of reject or prospect
of denial you stop engaging with that
and those thoughts become more apparent
thoughts I want to do this I want to say
this then if you stay with that and
don't act don't try to get rid of it
then you start saying ah all of this is
because the mind is enduring in such and
such state state the sensuality state to
the version state to delusion and you
don't want it you don't want you don't
want it but you realize if you say yes
or no to the symptoms you lose the side
of the illness which means you're
affected by it so to truly approach it
is to develop this passion towards that
mind that you discern through these
indications of it not through management
in control of your thinking relief it's
a huge planning it's usually you go
beyond basically you knew you fully
cannot be reached completely you go
beyond the domain of complaining
thoughts or sensual thoughts because
there is a whole indication that's why
further developing your mind resulting
in first jhana developing a mind results
in development of Samadhi but is a
result in imperturbable
because if if you have treated illness
can any symptom apply to you ever again
of that illness no it's inconceivable
its seclusion Chi to be vacant chi they
make it would be the kind of the
combination but again that's what I mean
so you need to be sense restrained and
virtuous then you actually need to be
physically secluded most of the time to
start discerning like seclusion
seclusion seclusion of my senses from
its object then seclusion of my from of
my mind from my thoughts but if you are
not even secluded from your sense
objects of a perception of others yeah
good luck secluding your mind from your
thoughts